RG 031, Connecticut Unemployment Commission
Connecticut State Library
Connecticut Unemployment Commission records
1931-1933
Connecticut State Library
Connecticut Unemployment Commission
11.5 cubic feet
The Commission worked with other state and federal agencies to investigate and mitigate the effects of the existing serious unemployment and to encourage employers to gather statistics and information with a view to finding a solution to the problem.
RG031
T001427
Historical Note
The Commission originated in December 1930 with the appointment, jointly by Governor Trumbull and Governor-elect Cross, or a committee to cooperate with other state and national agencies in investigating and mitigating the effects of the existing serious unemployment and to encourage employers to gather statistics and information with a view toward finding a solution to the problem. This group, named the Connecticut State Emergency Committee on Employment, was headed by James W. Hook, with Richard I. Neithercut as Executive Secretary. It held a number of meetings, conducted surveys of town and city activities, and reported its recommendations to the Governor on February 19, 1931.
In July 1931 the Committee was succeeded by the Connecticut Unemployment Commission, with almost identical membership and responsibilities, authorized by the General Assembly under Special Acts, 191, Ch. 468. It also held meetings, conducted surveys and educational programs, and reported its findings in Measures to Alleviate Unemployment in Connecticut (December 1932_). It maintained its office in Hartford Under Mr. Neithercut and an office in New Haven under Eleanor H. Little, Research Secretary. Like the earlier Committee, it attempted to stimulate and coordinate the work of local groups working in employment and relief problems and it served as the State point of contact for United states Government activities such as the Army distribution of salvaged clothing, the Farm Board sale of wheat and cotton, and the C.C.C. Employment program. In May 1933 the Federal Emergency Relief Act signaled the beginning of the major relief program, and the Connecticut General Assembly created the Connecticut Emergency Relief Commission on June 7, 1933, to handle federal relief funds and to supervise the issue of bonds by towns. The new agency therefore replaced the Unemployment Commission, which went out of existence at the end of June 1933.
Scope and Content
This record group includes the remaining archives of both the Connecticut State Emergency Committee on Employment and the Connecticut Unemployment Commission.
Related Material
RG 005:025, John Trumbull gubernatorial records.
RG 005:026, Wilbur Cross gubernatorial records.
RG 032, Emergency Relief Commission. Includes files of Civil Works Administration (CWA) and Federal Relief Administration (FERA) projects.
Published reports:
Report of the Connecticut State Emergency Committee on Employment… February 19, 1931. 11pp.
Measures to Alleviate Unemployment in Connecticut. A Report… from the Connecticut Unemployment Commission… December 1932. 205 pp.
and tables.
Index Terms
Organizations:
Connecticut Unemployment Commission
Subjects:
Connecticut Unemployment Commission -- Records and correspondence; Depressions -- 1929 -- Connecticut; Unemployed -- Connecticut
Document Types:
Account books; Clippings; Correspondence; Minutes; Questionnaires
Restrictions on Access
These records are stored at an off-site facility and therefore may not be available on a same-day basis.
See the policy.
Container List
- Records, 1931-1933
  - 1. Minutes of meetings, 1931 January 10-1933 June 27; 2 volumes (Box 1)
    Arranged chronologically.
  - 2. Expense books, 1931 January 22-1933 June 30 (Box 1)
    Includes two volumes of Committee and Commission administrative accounts, one volume of C.C.C. administration accounts, a group of voucher or check stubs and a group of Comptroller's statements. Also includes a journal (item 1a), October 1932-June 1933.
  - 3. General file, 1931 January-June
    Correspondence and owrking papers of the Emergency Committee on Employment, from the office of the Executive Secretary.
    - Correspondence with Governor Cross and with each Committee member (Box 2)
    - Free employment bureaus (Box 2)
      Survey reports and corresopndence.
      Alphabetical by town.
    - Hartford (Box 2)
      Correspondence with organizations in Hartford.
    - New Haven (Box 2)
      Correspondence with Institute of Human Relations, Yale University.
    - Payrolls and manhours (Box 2)
      Survey material.
    - State Capitol (Box 3)
      Correspondence with State Government agencies.
    - Washington, D.C. (Box 3)
      Correspondence with United States Government agencies.
    - Miscellaneous (Box 3-4)
      Arranged alphabetically by subject or correspondent.
  - 4. Survey file, 1930 December-1931 June
    Correspondence, questionnaires and working papers concerning surveys of unemployment organization and activities in the towns, and construction projects started or porjected in the towns.
    - Andover-Greenwich (Box 5)
    - Groton-Norwich (Box 6)
    - Old Lyme-Woodbury (Box 7)
  - 5. General file, 1931 July-1933 June
    Correspondence and working papers of the Unemployment Commission, mostly from the Hartford offices of the Executive Secretary.
    - Correspondence with Governor Cross, members of the Commission, Miss Little and Mr,. Neithercut (Box 8-9)
    - Free employment bureaus (Box 9)
    - Payroll and manhours (Box 10)
      Tabulations, followed by papers alphabetical by town or company.
    - State Capitol (Box 10)
    - General correspondence and working papers
      - A-B (Box 11)
      - C-Ga (Box 12)
      - Go-Na (Box 13)
      - Ne-Q (Box 14)
      - R-W (Box 15)
  - 6. Survey file, 1931 July-1933 June
    Correspondence, questionnaires and working papers concerning surveys of employment and relief work in the towns.
    - Andover-Cromwell (Box 16)
    - Danbury-Hartford (Box 17)
    - Hartland-New Haven (Box 18)
    - New London-Stafford (Box 19)
    - Stramford-Woodstock (Box 20)
  - 7. New Haven office papers, 1931 March-1933 July (Box 21)
    This is evidently a part of a classified file accumuilated in the New Haven ofifce, where both Mr. Hook, Chairman, and Miss Little, Research Secretary, were located. It includes correspndence and other materials on office administration and personnel, as well as minutes of meetings and reports of the Executive Secretary and the Research Secretary.
    Arranged by subject.
  - 8. Clippings, 1930 December-1932; 1 volume
    Mounted newspaper clippings pertaining to the work of the Commission and related matters.
    Chronological.
    - Scrapbook, 1930 December - 1932; 1 volume (Box Item 22)